<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Beans and Boobie Milk</title>
    <description>Educating the masses</description>
    <link>http://beansandboobiemilk.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://beansandboobiemilk.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Mon, 18 Apr 2016 02:14:43 -0400</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 18 Apr 2016 02:14:43 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.1.2</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Reasons to Breastfeed</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt; 

&lt;h2&gt;Reasons to breastfeed&lt;/h2&gt; 

&lt;p&gt;&lt;h1&gt;THAT HAVE NOTHING TO DO WITH YOUR BABY&#39;S HEALTH&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Breastfeeding rates and advocacy are on the rise, yay! Unfortunately, because this leaves some people feeling judged or attacked, breastfeeding is also under some scrutiny.  As a breastfeeding advocate, I simply want everyone to feel educated, encouraged, and supported. I don’t want anyone to feel like less of a woman or mother for not achieving  (or even setting) breastfeeding goals. That being said, I do take issue with some of the counter-points I’ve seen to the breastfeeding craze.

&lt;p&gt;People have taken to discounting the benefits of breastfeeding. I’ve seen more and more articles discussing that much of the research behind the facts that we shout from the rooftops isn’t as strong as once thought, and perhaps breastfeeding isn’t THAT much better for your baby than formula. As a mother, any opportunity to make my child smarter, closer to me, and healthier is an opportunity worth taking. However, those are my personal thoughts, and not something that all women feel. So, instead of going on and on about those health benefits (that all major health organizations including the WHO and CDC recognize), I’ve come up with a list of reasons you should breastfeed that have NOTHING to do with an infant’s health.

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;1.	The Environment.&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;
I spent hours researching the impact of formula on the environment. It was something I hadn’t really heard much about, and the numbers out there truly appalled me.  I make some pretty strong efforts to be environmentally conscious. I wash and reuse Ziploc bags, I bring reusable bags to every store, I limit my electricity use, etc. but even I was feeling pretty smug about my carbon footprint after looking deeper in to this topic. Anyways, about halfway through my summary, I realized I wasn’t contributing anything new to the conversation, and it would be better to simply direct you to the best resource I found: http://ibfan.org/docs/FormulaForDisaster.pdf To be clear, the impact of formula on the environment is so bad an international organization named their research paper Formula For Disaster. 

&lt;p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;	For those of you with limited time or attention spans-here are the highlights:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The key ingredient in formula is cow’s milk. Livestock (i.e. cows) are the largest contributor of methane and are currently considered one of the biggest contributing factors to global warming. Dairy farms also use a tremendous amount of water, land, and energy to run day to day. Milk then travels hundreds of miles (burning fuel), to the nearest factory where it is processed (burning through a variety of resources) to make it fit for infant consumption. Then it’s packaged in cardboard, plastic, and aluminum cans, which can’t be recycled. It’s estimated that 550 million of these bad boys enter landfills EACH YEAR. After being bought it’s mixed with water (water that comes from plastic jugs because distilled water is safest for infants to drink). Then, those very bottles formula is served in have to be washed, boiled, using up even more water, and are then eventually thrown away.  
From start to finish, infant formula is a threat to the environment. I recognize this route is the same route countless food items take in the American diet, so it shouldn’t be the only food being attacked. In general, we have a very unsustainable food system that is wreaking havoc on the planet. But, if there is any way any one of us can reduce our use of this system it is a step in the right direction. 

&lt;p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;
2.	Mom’s health
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;
You may not be impressed by some of the more moderate (though still present) benefits of breastfeeding for an infant, but what about for mothers? Breastfeeding reduces a woman’s risk of cancer. A woman can decrease her risk of breast cancer by 4% for every 12months of breastfeeding. That’s not all; ovarian cancer is also reduced by breastfeeding. One specific study found that women that breastfeed for at least 31 months have a 91% less chance of developing ovarian cancer compared to women that breastfed for less than 10 months. 
Breastfeeding also promotes weight loss!  By burning up to 500 calories each day, breastfeeding helps mothers return to a healthy post partum weight. 
http://www.mdanderson.org/patient-and-cancer-information/cancer-information/cancer-topics/prevention-and-screening/health/breastfeeding.html

&lt;p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;
3.	Emergency preparedness
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;
I know this may feel extreme but natural disasters are on the rise (thanks to global warming)! Relying on formula to feed your infant means you are dependent on several systems to work perfectly: milk has to be available, factories have to be running, roads have to be safe, stores have to be open and stocked, and water has to be clean. That’s so many moving pieces. We all like to think nothing will happen to us, but it can. And if it does, breastfeeding may be the only thing that keeps your children alive. Here are two examples of how breastfeeding saved the lives, not only of children, but also of other adults in a dire situation.
http://abcnews.go.com/Health/story?id=2701717&amp;amp;page=1
http://articles.chicagotribune.com/2001-02-07/news/0102070109_1_milk-puerto-rico-currents


&lt;p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;
4.	Money
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;
You all knew this was coming, and I realize it’s pretty low hanging fruit. FORMULA IS EXPENSIVE.  Most estimates out there calculate a yearly cost anywhere from $1,200-$2,000 depending on the brand and eating habits of each infant. There is something else to be consider financially, but bringing it up kind of feels like cheating because I swore this wouldn’t be about infant health. But I’m going to bring it up anyways. Formulas fed infants are more likely to get sick, and develop earaches. And that means that mothers of formula fed infants are more likely to miss work to stay home and care for their sick children. 

&lt;p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;
5.	 Sleep
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;
In my experience, fear of sleep deprivation is a common concern for everyone involved with a baby. Friends and family are constantly asking if the baby sleeps through the night yet, while parents are constantly setting up game plans to survive each 24 hour cycle (there are no days and nights in those first few weeks). It may surprise you to know that breastfeeding mothers actually sleep more than formula feeding mothers!  Studies vary on how much more, but it tends to fall in the 20-45 minute range each night. In this particular study, breastfeeding mothers also expressed feeling better rested than their counter formula feeding mothers. 
http://www.kathleenkendall-tackett.com/CLKendall-tackett_ppd_fatigue_bf.pdf  

&lt;p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;
6.	Contamination
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Formula is a product of human hands, and as such, mistakes happen. Recalls are rare, but can you imagine the fear as a new mom? There you are, happily feeding you precious bundle of joy when all of the sudden you hear that his only food source is contaminated. Again, this isn’t common, but it DOES happen. And it’s gross. Proof:
http://www.cleveland.com/business/index.ssf/2010/09/similac_recall_check_here_to_s.html http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2012/03/13/gerber-recall_n_1341353.html

&lt;p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;
7.	Damn the Man!
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Formula companies are BIG BUSINESS (to the tune of $3 billion). Though first created to help save lives, it quickly became an alternative to breastfeeding (instead of a last resort). Marketed to the public, endorsed by doctors, and handed out for free in hospitals as a “just as healthy if not better than” option, formula became the norm in the first half of the 20th century. Medical professionals agree that the advertising of formula has changed the infant feeding climate, and led to poorer breastfeeding rates, and thus poorer health of our children.  It may be a bit petty of me, but I just HATE that someone out there is making millions of dollars by convincing women to doubt their own capabilities as mothers. So I say fuck ‘em. 
PLEASE LOOK AT THIS LINK&amp;lt;a href=http://www.slate.com/articles/double_x/doublex/2015/06/a_century_of_formula_advertising_it_s_always_gone_straight_for_the_new_mother.html&amp;gt;, so understand my point here! It’s fascinating. 

http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC2684040/
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 20 Jan 2016 08:58:35 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://beansandboobiemilk.com/Reasons to Breasfeed</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://beansandboobiemilk.com/Reasons to Breasfeed</guid>
        
        
        <category>Breastfeeding</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>What My Baby Eats</title>
        <description>&lt;h1&gt;What My Baby Eats&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m a firm believer in waiting until infants are 6 months old to start solids. Antiquated practices recommended starting as early as 4 months, and I still get clients that are told to put cereal in their 2 month olds bottles! Science has proven that a baby’s digestive system is not ready for complex foods before 6 months, and offering foods too early puts the child at risk for food allergies later in life https://www.healthychildren.org/English/ages-stages/baby/feeding-nutrition/Pages/Cereal-in-a-Bottle-Solid-Food-Shortcuts-to-Avoid.aspx

&lt;p&gt;So, up until June, Rosalind had only ever consumed boobie milk or water. At 5 months I remember saying to several people, “I just don’t know if we will make it to 6 months. She is so hungry, and she reaches and stares at the foods Rob and I eat.” Everyone was supportive of me starting early. Each time I considered caving I researched once more and found more information on the importance of waiting. The WHO, the CDC, the AAP, all of them say to wait. So instead I started a sippy cup of water at meal times. While it’s important to make sure water is never offered in place of a nutritional feeding, this step got her used to her sippy cup early on, and kept her content at meal times when Rob and I ate. I would estimate she never drank more than ½ an ounce in a day. From here on out, you can trust the only thing she has ever drank other then milk, is water.  We were nursing 10 times every day, and I was comfortable with this routine. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;6 months&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It just so happened that Roz was 6 months and 5 days on Father’s Day! That felt like a fun occasion to celebrate with a new milestone. I think I cried for 20 minutes imagining her perfect breastfed tummy being contaminated with food. Obviously this was ridiculous but new moms aren’t exactly known for being sane… anyways, I bit the bullet and was happier for it. She didn’t eat much, but she was fascinated by the experience and so excited to be at the big kid table together with Mom and Dad. Her first food was acorn squash. I had made a small batch of baby foods back in January when squash was still cheap in preparation for this day. She seemed to understand the spoon, and quickly got the hang of opening her mouth when she was ready for another bite. Again, following AAP guidelines, we offered 1 new food every 3-5 days so we could identify an allergy if she broke out in rash, or diarrhea, etc. We focused on vegetables for the entire first month of foods. In Rosalind’s first month of foods she tried acorn squash, butternut squash, sweet potato, zucchini, carrot, and cauliflower. Some days she ate a teaspoon, some days she ate a tablespoon. We stuck with nursing all day, but would try a solid at dinnertime.  If she was still hungry after a tablespoon of food we nursed again. We were still nursing about 8 times each day.

&lt;p&gt;Some of you may be wondering why her first food wasn’t rice cereal. I made this decision after reading about baby-led weaning (BLW). The BLW process involves introducing children to table foods first, and skipping any type of puree. BLW users believe learning to chew and then swallow is a healthier pattern than learning the other way around. I get it, and I support it, but that scared the crap out of me and I quickly decided that wouldn’t work for us. However, much of the literature on BLW discusses skipping cereals not only because they aren’t chewed, but also because they are too bland. BLW suggests that when a baby’s first food is basically plain cardboard, bold flavors like vegetables become even scarier. This made sense to me, so we rode that wave. 



&lt;h1&gt;7 months&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By 7 months Roz was routinely finishing a tablespoon of food at dinner. We started on fruits next and cruised through pears, peaches, plums, banana, and apple without a hitch. Grapes (don’t worry they were chopped in a million ways to prevent choking) gave her diarrhea. That actually ended up being awesome though because when she had her first experience with constipation I knew exactly how to clear it up! I decided it was time to increase her food intake and began offering a solid at breakfast and dinner. I also started continuing to feed her solids until she refused. Sometimes she would eat 2-3 tablespoons of food at one sitting, so I knew she preferred this to the never ended breastfeeding sessions we were sitting through day in and day out.  We still nursed at least 6 times daily. 

&lt;h1&gt;8 months&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We advanced to 3 meals each day when Roz turned 8 months old. She was eating nearly every fruit and vegetable out there by then, and trying to eat my own lunch without giving her any was no longer an option. She continued to try new foods like kale, spaghetti squash, white potato, and berries. I started leaving foods less mashed, and even gave her small chunks to pick up and feed herself. She took to this quickly, and soon she preferred to feed herself half her meal. She would get tired of the struggle and request some spoon-feeding assistance eventually, but her skills improved every day. It’s amazing how content she was with plain produce. I kept thinking I should add some herbs to her vegetables, but she ate them so happily I didn’t see a reason to. It was such reinforcement that infants are a product of the world around them. She can’t prefer really buttery potatoes or cheese on her broccoli if she has never had it! We still nursed at least 5 times each day.

&lt;h1&gt;9 months&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;9 months meant it was time for proteins! This is scary subject for a dietitian, because I’ve been taught about allergens. Traditionally, parents used to be encouraged to offer only the yolk of eggs, and avoid all nuts and peanuts to reduce the risk of allergies. In my research, the medical world is split. There is research that supports starting those foods early to get the body used to them, and research that says it’s best to wait. Neither Rob nor I have food allergies in our immediate family, so I went bold. We started offering eggs, nuts and peanut butter along with occasional meats all in this time frame. 

&lt;p&gt;My daughter has literally never eaten a plain egg. Each morning we get up and I dice up some vegetables to include in her little baby scramble. Tomatoes, bell pepper, spinach, potato-anything I can do to start her day balanced and nutrient dense! Beans became my go-to snack. I could serve them cut in half and they were a good size for her pincer grasp,  but also small enough to not be a choking hazard. She ate beans before meals if she was getting antsy, and as a snack if we were out and she didn’t want to nurse.  

&lt;p&gt;I also started grains in her 9th month. Her eating skills were advanced enough I felt she could handle them, and I was struggling to keep meals new and exciting with only fruits, vegetables, and egg in the mix! I made her oatmeal from fresh oats about once a week, it usually fed her three times. I usually mix in peanut butter and applesauce or bananas and it’s a perfect meal. We also gave her plain noodles to feed herself, and brown rice from a spoon. We tried baked goods like tortilla and bread but she wasn’t too interested at this age. 

&lt;p&gt;Coincidentally, I also got my period back for the first time. As nursing became less of a focus, my hormones decided it was safe for me to start menstruating again. This was a huge bummer, obviously, because periods are the worst. Also, it meant her dependency on me was lowering, and as a mother that’s tough to know. Don’t worry though; we were still nursing at least 4 times every day! 

&lt;h1&gt;10 months&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once Roz turned 10 months old I just threw it all to the birds. This girl would eat a plain vegetable she found in the dirt, was able to feed herself almost any food I put on her tray, and started eating insanely large portions. We progressed to simply giving her what we are eating and haven’t looked back. This transition has been great for us, because it’s an extra motivator for me to make balanced meals. I mean, I’m a dietitian so that means 90% of our meals were already healthy, but I can’t deny the occasional dinner of only macaroni and cheese. Now there is a fruit or vegetable at EVERY SINGLE MEAL, even if it’s a more unbalanced (high calorie, low nutrient density...macaroni and cheese basically) meal for the adults. Feeding Rosalind entirely from our meals has also been a time saver and stress reducer. No more baby foods, no more separate containers, no more feeling like I’m cooking a 6-course meal every night. We all eat together and talk about our days like a bona-fide family. Which makes sense, because we are one.  Still nursing 4 times every day. 

&lt;p&gt;As you may have guessed from the macaroni and cheese reference, we also introduced dairy. I still try to take it easy on this, as she only needs mom’s milk, but feeding her from our own meals meant Rob and I were missing dairy too. She definitely likes cheese, and it’s been nice to be able to turn to a sprinkle of shredded cheese as a snack if I don’t have any beans ready. 

&lt;h1&gt;11 months&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’ve continued to progress the type of food she can handle. Before if we had a combination item, like pizza, I would break it down in to crust, vegetable topping, and cheese for her to eat. Now we give her small bites of the whole concoction. She’s impressed me with her abilities to handle these advanced foods.  By now she is familiar with bold foods too. Curry, stir fry, fajitas, you name it! She has her father’s taste buds so far, which means she will eat anything you put in front of her with a smile on her face. 

&lt;h1&gt;12 months&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was in a deep internal struggle with how we would celebrate Rosalind’s first birthday. With birthday parties come birthday cake…remember how I actually cried before I fed my baby plain acorn squash? You can imagine the turmoil I felt behind introducing her to sugar! It seems like NOT a big deal. You offer her a plain slice of angel food cake, she probably won’t even like it, and your baby still loves vegetables. On the other hand though, what’s the point? Until now I’ve made a special effort to ensure that everything she eats serves a nutritional purpose. Tragically-cake doesn’t fit that standard.  I considered a sweet bread like banana nut? At least there’s a fruit and some omega 3 fats in there! I went back and forth each day and finally landed on no cake for baby Roz. I got some flack for this, but I stand by my choice. She got to blow out a candle, and was having so much fun being cheered for she didn’t even notice when I pulled the cupcake back out of grasp. The day will come when she can have 5 cupcakes if that’s what she chooses, but it wasn’t on her first birthday. She will never care and I slept easier knowing I stuck to my own comfort level.  

&lt;h1&gt;Now&lt;/h1&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;Rosalind is now finding she has preferences when it comes to food. She turns down entrees because she doesn’t like them, and seems to eat larger portions when it’s something she does like. When I make a meal and she is disappointed I turn to butternut squash cubes I have pre-diced in my freezer, applesauce (no sugar added of course), and cheese. She loves all of these foods, and I know they will fill her up while giving her most food groups and minimal junk.  She is still nursing 4 times each day, but I foresee 1 of those sessions dropping off in the coming weeks. We still only drink water. She was given a bite of cookie at my family’s Christmas Eve gathering much to my dismay, but we have recovered and have not reintroduced sugar. I still don’t see the point. When you see a child pound down clementines like she does, you feel pretty confident she isn’t missing out on anything.&lt;/p&gt; 

&lt;h2&gt;Note!&lt;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most important thing when feeding an infant is safety. A baby should never be left alone with food unsupervised, and you should always follow your baby’s cues for what he or she can handle. Do not push advanced textures on an infant that isn’t interested. They are letting you know they aren’t ready, and that’s ok! As long as your baby is learning about meal times, learning about healthy food items, and is growing, you’re doing a great job of feeding your baby. Enjoy the journey, embrace the messes, and do your best to ignore the fact that nearly everything you’ve eaten in the last 4 months has been lukewarm. They won’t let you feed them forever, and you’ll miss it when it’s gone. 
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 18 Jan 2016 08:58:35 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://beansandboobiemilk.com/What My Baby Eats</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://beansandboobiemilk.com/What My Baby Eats</guid>
        
        
        <category>Nutrition</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Breastfeeding Advocate</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;As society turns more and more to breastfeeding as the new normal (or old normal depending on who you talk to), the term “breastfeeding advocate” gets used quite a bit. I consider myself to be a breastfeeding advocate, but I’ve come to realize that means different things to different people. It’s important that you understand my stance on breastfeeding and how I advocate, so you know what role I can play in your breastfeeding experience. 

&lt;p&gt;Being a breastfeeding advocate means I refer to formula as the lesser product instead of breastmilk as the better product. When you compare breastmilk to formula, it implies that formula is the baseline, and breastmilk is a better option. That continues the climate of formula being the normal way to feed the baby while breastfeeding is an alternative. We need to change that dialogue and compare formula to breastmilk. Breastmilk doesn’t lower your child’s risk of cancer, formula raises is. Breastmilk isn’t cheaper than formula, formula is more expensive. I admit, sometimes this wording sounds harsh and aggressive towards formula and that isn’t my goal. I simply believe it’s a more accurate way of discussing a mother’s options for feeding her baby. It establishes a platform of breastfeeding, with formula as support beams instead of the other way around. 

&lt;p&gt;As a breastfeeding advocate I educate everyone about breastfeeding. Why, how, when, for how long, where, etc. And not just general tidbits here.  Nearly people know “breastmilk is better for the baby,” but they can’t tell me specifics reasons. If I’ve been educating a woman on the benefits of breastfeeding, I want her to walk away knowing details like formula increases her child’s risk of ear infections, SIDS, and type 2 diabetes. This type of information is much more motivating and valuable than a simple, “it’s healthier” mentality. If someone asks me how long I’m going to breastfeed I don’t start with my personal goals, I start with “The WHO recommends all children be breastfed until at least age 2,” so continue getting the information spread to anyone that will listen.

&lt;p&gt;Breastfeeding advocacy also means I’m going to congratulate and praise any woman I see breastfeeding in public. If breastfeeding is going to stop being a taboo topic, the population needs to see it happen. Millions of children are being nursed every second of every day, (that’s not a researched fact but it seems accurate, right?) yet most people that I have breastfed in front of tell me it’s the first time they’ve ever seen it done. No wonder breastfeeding seems weird to people! The thought of seeing a baby suckle at a woman’s breast can illicit some bizarre mental images until you see it in person. Then, suddenly it’s a beautiful image of nature and maternal instinct. I’ve only been given praise one time for breastfeeding in public and I literally started crying it made me so happy! I can only imagine what it feels like to woman with less confidence in her breastfeeding ways. I make an effort to applaud all women for breastfeeding out in the open for the world to see and admire.

&lt;p&gt;If you aren’t comfortable breastfeeding in public, breastfeeding advocacy means I’m going to bend over backwards to give you a safe and private space to feed your baby. Sometimes women feel exposed while nursing, sometimes they feel indecent, and sometimes the baby is just too wild to be around outside stimulation for a nursing session. All of that is ok, and you should feel just as supported by me as the woman whipping her boob out at the dinner table. I’ll wait in line for a dressing room, I’ll hold up a blanket in the corner, I’ll tell the pervert staring at you to…well you can imagine. I just want you to feed your baby how you want to, where you want to, when you want to. 

&lt;p&gt;If you invite me to your baby shower, I’m going to buy you breastfeeding accessories. I could care less about a cute onesie or rattle. I’m buying you a support pillow, a bra, some milk bags-something that will help your chances of success. I’ll always give you a gift receipt so you don’t have to awkwardly ask where I bought it so you can return it because you’re planning on formula feeding.  Just remember, one nursing pillow costs the same as 2 cans of formula, so even if you only nurse for 2 weeks-it paid for itself!

&lt;p&gt;As an advocate, I could talk about breastfeeding all day long. And I want to. If you need breastfeeding help, PLEASE ASK ME. I’m a bottomless pit of encouragement, support, facts, tips and tricks, you name it. I must have texted my lactation consultant (a dear friend’s mother) once a day for 3 weeks when I was first getting the hang of it. I’m not sure I would have made it through without her. Support is everything on those challenging days and a breastfeeding advocate should be that for all breastfeeding moms. Nothing upsets me more than meeting a woman that just needed on more person cheering her on to help her achieve her breastfeeding goals. I could have been that person! And more importantly, I wanted to be that person. 

&lt;p&gt;Breastfeeding advocacy DOESN’T mean that I think less of a woman for formula feeding her baby. Formula is a priceless substance that has saved countless baby’s lives, and I’m so grateful for its existence. It plays an important role in our world and I value that, truly I do. All mothers want what is best for their infants, and if a woman can confidently say that formula is the best for her family, so be it. I think terrible things about the guerilla marketing tactics used by formula companies, but that’s not the issue here. The fact is that formula is an essential option for millions of mothers, and hallelujah for it and the mothers that deal with it. Scrubbing all those bottles, carrying around those giant cans, dealing with the smellier poop-they all deserve a medal really. 
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 07 Dec 2015 08:58:35 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://beansandboobiemilk.com/Breastfeeding Advocate</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://beansandboobiemilk.com/Breastfeeding Advocate</guid>
        
        
        <category>Breastfeeding</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Meatless</title>
        <description>&lt;h1&gt;The importance of going meatless&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;     I believe in eating meat because of the basic food chain&lt;/strong&gt;. Humans are at the top, and it makes sense that we consume those below us, just like many mammals on the planet. However, we know that meat is not necessary for survival, particularly in the amounts that the USA eats. In 2007 the average American ate 270 pounds of meat each year. Doesn’t sound like too much to you? Let’s do the math. To eat 270 pounds in 365 days a person has to eat around 12oz of meat EVERY DAY. That’s four, 3oz portions-we only eat 3 meals a day! As a comparison, Indians, which have the lowest meat consumption, averaged 7 pounds of meat in a year. 2.5% of what Americans ate. I like bacon as much as the next girl, but come on. There is NO way that my cravings for bacon can be justified when weighed with the damage it does to my health, my wallet, and my earth. And yours don’t either. The classic “meat and potatoes” meal has taken over our concept of a balanced meal, but it’s time to make a change. If you aren&#39;t making efforts to go meatless occasionally, it&#39;s time to start. You will save money, and you will be taking necessary steps towards protecting your own health, along with the health of the entire planet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If everyone in the US went meatless for 1 day we would save 100 billion gallons of water, and 70 million gallons of gas. That’s about 18% of all the gas consumed by Americans each day. How could something as simple as choosing a salad over a burger impact the planet so much? Here’s how:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Raising livestock blows through resources including water, electricity, and land at a tremendous rate. Even though we squeeze those guys in as small a space as possible, animals need room, food, and water to grow. And when you&#39;re raising enough animals to feed the more than 300 million people in this country, the resource needs are extremely high. Cows, specifically, consume 16 times more grain than meat they produce. What a bizarre system. We produce pounds of edible and nutritious food in order to get 1/16th of the food back. It takes 5,000 gallons of water to produce 1 pound of beef compared to 49 gallons for 1 pound of apples-yet 783 million people worldwide don’t even have access to clean water for themselves. 80% of Brazil&#39;s deforestation is for soy (which feeds cattle) and cattle themselves. Humans are literally tearing down the Amazon rainforest, home to 10% of the world’s animal species and 20% of the world’s bird species, so that we can feed and house more cows. I care WAY more about the survival rates of those species than I do about you or I having a meatball with our spaghetti. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eating meat is a top contributor to global warming as well. Livestock produce more greenhouse gases than all forms of transportation combined. And yes, it&#39;s basically from toots. Not to be harder on cattle than any other animals, but they really are the biggest culprits. If you&#39;ve ever driven past a cattle farm you are familiar with the stench of cow toots. And those toots are filled with methane gas, which is 23 times more powerful than CO2. Not to mention the decline of air quality as trees are cut down (remember those deforestation numbers from before) to make more land for those cows to toot on. If you don’t believe that global warming is a real threat to society by now, well, you deserve to be thrown in to the Artic to feed the starving polar bears. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I get it though, environmental impacts are hard to use as motivation to make life changes. I’m a hippie and a tree hugger and blah blah blah. Most struggle to recognize the impact they would make on their own amongst the millions of other people not making changes. Your own health is on the line too, and that&#39;s something I hope most of you see the value in. If you’ve ever said, “CANCER AND HEART DISEASE?! Those sound scary and awful, I would love to do everything in my power to avoid those terrible health complications,” you’re in luck! Studies all over the world have shown a direct link between meat consumption and increased cancer and cardiovascular death. In a change that made headlines just a few months ago, the WHO officially listed processed meats in the same category as cigarettes for being known carcinogens, and red meat as a likely carcinogen. One study by Harvard found that each routine, daily serving of red meat increased a person’s risk of death by 13%. Don&#39;t forget too, when you eat less meat you eat more plants. Plants in the diet are proven to lower cancer risk, as well as improve cholesterol levels and blood pressure. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, because this is opinion and not based on fact, animals don&#39;t deserve to be treated how they are by the meat industry. Tight spaces, brutal and sometimes painful deaths, unnatural diets, no access to fresh air, etc. It&#39;s just not humane. And though I admit, I care more about beautiful Amazonian big cats than I do pigs, I still don’t want any of them to suffer. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sold on cutting down your meat intake, but not sure how to start? Here are some easy steps towards a reduced meat lifestyle:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;1. Mix your ground meat with beans. Black, pinto, or white can easily be mashed in to ground turkey or hamburger with minimal taste or texture changes. Imagine if every pound of meat magically lasted for twice as many meals. Plus you get the bonus of increased fiber intake from those nutritional power houses-the bean.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2. Cut out only beef entirely. I&#39;m sure you figured out from the statistics that beef is the worst meat all around.  From your health to the environment, giving up beef will make a huge impact that is sure to last. Any recipe calling for ground beef can be replaced with ground turkey or chicken with only subtle changes in flavor. Add a bit of olive oil to the meat before cooking, it will keep it juicy while giving you that heart healthy dose of Omega 3s.&lt;/p&gt; 

&lt;p&gt;3. Eat wild game. I can&#39;t get on board with this because of Bambi and social norms, however! Getting meat from animals that are living in the wild eliminates nearly all of the environmental damage. Deer, specifically, are overpopulated and honestly need to be eaten more so they will leave my plants alone...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4. Change the meat and produce ratio. Whenever I cook an omnivorous recipe I halve the meat and double the vegetable. Making chicken noodle soup?  1/2 pound of chicken to 2 cups of carrots, 1 cup of celery and onion. A lunchtime BLT? Use only 2 slices of bacon, add an extra slice of tomato, and a hearty smear of avocado.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good luck. And seriously, please, &lt;strong&gt;eat more rabbit food.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 20 Nov 2015 08:58:35 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://beansandboobiemilk.com/Meatless</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://beansandboobiemilk.com/Meatless</guid>
        
        
        <category>Nutrition</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Baby aisle</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I haven’t spent much time in the baby food aisle. Breastfeeding and making your own baby food means you don’t need anything down that lane. However, I’m a pediatric dietitian, and my career is teaching parents how to feed their children well. Parents often ask what is best for their little ones to eat because it&#39;s so hard to wade through the hundreds of options on the shelves. I try to make an effort to go down that row at the grocery store at least once a month, so I know what decisions these parent have to make each day. I’ve started to really hold a grudge against that aisle. With extreme cost mark ups, and strategic wording, baby food companies are truly taking advantage of the only thing that unites all parents-the desire to raise a healthy baby. So, here are the items I educate on the most, so parents can make informed decisions on their feeding choices.

&lt;p&gt;Baby juice is not real. Well, it is real, but there isn&#39;t an actual need for it in the market place. It&#39;s just regular juice with a baby brand on the label. Most importantly, JUICE IS NOT GOOD FOR BABIES. Infants need to develop a taste for water, and I promise that won&#39;t go well if the alternative is sweet, colorful, and flavorful. You know when you think you&#39;re going to drink Sprite, but it&#39;s actually water? The water tastes like poison at first. Once you know it is water you can drink it happily. The same thing happens to infants that get juice while they are learning about water. If they try water and don&#39;t like it parents are quick to offer juice. From that moment on, water will always taste worse than something else. If they simply continue to drink water, they will eventually love it. Not only that, but juice often leads to tooth decay, diarrhea, and rashes. Water is the only beverage other than breastmilk or formula any child under the age of one should receive. Small amounts of juice can be used to naturally alleviate constipation, or as a very occasional (1 time a week or less) treat once the child is 1. It should never be offered every day. Ever. 

&lt;p&gt;I also don&#39;t believe in infant puffs. Yes they are a great size for little fingers, yes their dissolving nature makes them less of a choking hazard, but those are pretty much their only benefit. Otherwise they are filled with chemicals, sugar, and not much else. These seem to be a go-to snack for parents, but how do you expect your child to feel full when they aren&#39;t eating any fat, protein, or fiber? In reality, puffs tend to be used as a temporary babysitter. “Oh my kid is fussing? Just throw him some of these sweet cardboard chunks and he will settle right down.” In my opinion, they teach children to eat when they are bored, eat sweets all day, and snack mindlessly.

&lt;p&gt;My favorite baby snack is beans. Beans are cheap, fast, and easy to pack. I simply open a can of bean (any variety) give them a good rinse to reduce the sodium levels, and store them in the fridge. I fill a small Tupperware before we leave the house and keep it in my diaper bag. Though they aren&#39;t as shelf stable as a puff, I feel safe giving them to her 3-4 hours after they have left the fridge. I also give her beans when she is waiting for dinner in her high chair at home and at restaurants. I break them in half so they are a safe size to eat, but still big enough for her fingers to grip. She delightfully feeds herself, or the dog, while waiting patiently for the rest of dinner. This routine leaves us both happy and able to enjoy mealtimes together. I know beans are a weird food. They are mushy on the inside, have a pungent flavor, and they kind of look like tiny bugs. BUT, they are also incredibly good for you. The offer fiber and protein to help a baby feel full. They are also a source of iron, folate, and magnesium. Giving my baby beans on a regular basis means that not only is she benefitting from actual nutrition when she snacks, but also she will grow up comfortable and, hopefully, loving them through her childhood!

&lt;p&gt;My strongest hatred for baby products is formula designed &quot;for supplementing.&quot;  Several brands make it, and it&#39;s marketed for women that are breastfeeding, but are starting to use formula occasionally. Recipe wise, this means the company has added pre or probiotics in an effort to mimic breastmilk&#39;s immune support (*hint, they are failing). Marketing wise this is another attempt to set breastfeeding women up for failure. When you have a newborn and you&#39;re tired, nervous, and unsure, seeing a product that enforces supplementing is one more drop of doubt in your already overflowing I Cant Do This bucket. It makes a woman let her guard down about formula, because &quot;this one is different and more like breastmilk than those others formulas.&quot; There aren&#39;t any warnings on the can that remind the mom that supplementing with formula typically leads to quitting breastfeeding forever. Seeing that product on the shelves has a similar effect to being handed a sample from your doctor at a newborn check up: mothers think they are supposed to be using it, and that their milk isn&#39;t good enough after all. It&#39;s one thing to make a conscious decision to start supplementing, but it&#39;s completely different to decide to start supplementing because the product exists. Formula is formula, and you are less likely to succeed at breastfeeding once you start using it.

&lt;p&gt;On a happier note, I do have to give a shout out to baby food pouches. I’ve only used these while traveling, but they were a lifesaver. I do think that these pouches are changing the ways kids are eating produce in an amazing way. Parents are turning to these as snacks instead of chips and fruit snacks. Kids are eating kale with a smile on their face. Fruit and vegetable pouches are helping make produce an on-the-go food, which was once the biggest argument against them. I see kids from 1 to 12 sucking these guys down, and I am 100% behind them. Please always check your labels to make sure there are no added sugars. If the flavor is white bean, squash, and kale. The ingredient list should be pretty straight forward-white bean, squash, kale. I would also encourage parents to use the reusable, make your own variety. The premade pouches create a great deal of waste, but I’ll leave that alone for now. My focus is getting your kids to eat their veggies, and if eating them from a foil bag is the best way for now, so be it! Suck away-no word play intended.  

&lt;p&gt;When it comes to feeding your baby, remember that they are tiny humans. They don’t need special dissolvable snacks, or fancy drinks because they are bored with water. They need well-balanced meals made of real food. If it comes in a package, it probably comes with chemicals, additives, or dyes that are best to avoid. Feed them breastmilk, only feed them formula if you have to. Once they are old enough, give them water, if they won’t drink it they aren’t thirsty. Feed them vegetables, fruits, whole grains, and lean proteins. Sound familiar? It should, because it’s what every human needs, babies included. Labels, brand names, and kiddie-words exist not to make your child healthier, but to take your money faster. 
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 18 Nov 2015 08:58:35 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://beansandboobiemilk.com/Before</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://beansandboobiemilk.com/Before</guid>
        
        
        <category>Baby</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Before I even got pregnant...</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Before I even got pregnant, I knew I would plan to have my babies without pain medications. I like knowing my strengths as a woman, and I saw no better way to test my mental and physical limit than to deliver a baby naturally. Now that I’m on the other side of that goal, I can’t say enough positive things about the experience. I encourage every woman that asks to deliver without pain medications, and I’m quite vocal about my positive experience. 

&lt;p&gt;Pain medications have a pretty serious benefit…they make it so you don’t feel the almost indescribable pain of pushing a baby out of your vagina. That right there is a pretty big win, and I know that’s enough of a reason to make up your mind as soon as you find out you’re pregnant. Delivery is the toughest part of early parenthood and anything you can do to make it easier seems great. However, it doesn’t come without it’s drawbacks. 

&lt;p&gt;A huge motivator for me was cost. If I had chosen to have an epidural I would have had an additional $1200 bill. At the time I planned to go back to work, and $1200 was enough money saved to let me take my full 12-week FMLA leave. That decision mattered even more when we decided I would only go back to work part-time. I’m also exposed to horror stories occasionally, because I work with postpartum women every day. Though rare, epidurals can cause permanent damage, heart attacks, and blood pressure drops that lead to high-risk delivery
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 18 Nov 2015 08:58:35 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://beansandboobiemilk.com/Before</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://beansandboobiemilk.com/Before</guid>
        
        
        <category>First</category>
        
        <category>Post</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Thorough Introduction</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I was born and raised in Indiana. With obesity on both sides of my family and a nasty divorce between my parents, my sister and I were quick to become overweight children. I was an extremely picky eater accepting a small list of foods that consisted of macaroni and cheese, grilled cheese, spaghetti, and ramen noodles. I was a real brat when it came to meals; I’m not sure how my parents ever put up with me.

&lt;p&gt;In the fifth grade I realized I was overweight. I remember coming home from school and running around my block one time to get some exercise in. I would run in whatever I wore to school. I’m sure everyone on my block thought I was playing a long distance game of hide and seek. Still though, nutrition wasn’t something I knew or understood. 

&lt;p&gt;In middle school I elected to do a project on nutrition. This was when I first learned the value of a balanced plate. I started making efforts to try new foods, choke down the ones I hated, and think about the volumes I was consuming. I was still heavier than most girls my age, but felt pretty happy with myself. I bought a bikini for the first time, and I was no longer only wearing spandex because nothing else fit. 

&lt;p&gt;In high school I was a working athlete with beautiful friends. Though I never dealt with an eating disorder, there was certainly some disordered eating (by myself or my friends). Skipping breakfast, lunch or both, feeling guilty about eating dessert, trying to eat less in front of boys, etc. Despite being active, hardworking, and growing girls we were all very concerned with our size and appearance because, well, high school. Do I really need to explain more? I was still the biggest girl in my group, but when you hang out with all size 3s being a size 9 seems fat, which certainly didn’t help my self-esteem. I realized that my passion for cooking and eating was greater than the other girls. Everyone loves pizza night, but I thought about what toppings we would get all day, while everyone else stressed about how few slices they would eat. I started to embrace my bigger build and passion for foods. Why was I skipping breakfast when that’s my favorite meal of the day? I decided to go to culinary school and make my whole life’s theme food.

&lt;p&gt;Turns out, culinary school wasn’t in the cards for me. The only in-state option was in a very far away and small town, and I just wanted a more traditional college experience. I decided to attend Indiana University (Go Hoosiers!) and chose to major in dietetics. This ended up being the perfect major for me. My life’s theme is still food, but with the bonus twist of science and health. I was a great student; I earned a 3.8, was on dean’s list every semester, and was in the honor’s society.  Meanwhile I met my future husband, Rob, sophomore year, and lived with him senior year. 

&lt;p&gt;Upon graduating from IU I applied for 5 internships and matched with Saint Louis University as a pediatric intern. It was a one-year internship that was also paired with a year of graduate night school. I hated the idea of a thesis, private catholic college is HELLA expensive, and Rob proposed, so I chose to come back to Bloomington after completing my internship (instead of completing a Master’s in nutrition as well). 

&lt;p&gt;As a pediatric intern I spent nearly 50% of my internship in the Saint Louis Children’s Hospital. And yes, that word “in” is appropriate. I felt like I lived there. This experience reaffirmed my passion for infant and childhood nutrition, but totally changed my tune about clinical dietetics. I hate hospitals, even when they are covered in cartoons and primary colors. I hate the smell, the logistics, the charting, and most importantly, the suffering. I realized my favorite rotations were in the community setting. Reaching out to families that truly need help and education, and ensuring children are able to grow up with access to healthy meals was what I enjoyed doing.

&lt;p&gt;I came home and feverishly planned my wedding while studying for the Registered Dietitian exam. I passed my test on my first try (yahoo), got married in September, and started an aggressive job hunt. It took me 3 months to find a single position for an RD within 45 miles of my house. And wouldn’t you know, it was a position working with pregnant and post partum women, as well as children! I couldn’t believe my luck. Then I was the only applicant and they had no choice but to hire me! It was only part-time, but it was something. And I loved doing it. I was able to attend a breastfeeding training course where I earned my Certified Lactation Specialist title, the first step in becoming an IBCLC. The part-time position advanced to a full-time traveling position 8 months later, and my life was moving along as perfectly as I’d ever planned. 

&lt;p&gt;My husband and I bought a house together…and we were surprised with a pregnancy 4 weeks later. I was in shock. Rob was elated. After the initial surprise, my shock turned to elation too and I had a wonderful pregnancy. Rosalind was born in December 2014, healthy and happy. My job let me bring her with me to work for the first 6 months of her life, as a support to my breastfeeding lifestyle. I started back locally, part-time to ease in to this new routine, and had a scare on a snowy road while she was in the backseat. All at once I realized that having her in the car while I drove all over the state wasn’t just going to make my workday very stressful, it was putting her in danger. After a very emotional phone call with Rob, we decided that day I would return to only part-time work. We wrote a new and much less fun budget, and Roz and I skipped around the house in celebration. 

&lt;p&gt;So here I am now. A Mrs., an RD, a CLS, and a SAHM. Those titles tell you so much about me! I love food, I love nutrition, and I love educating people about both. I love breastfeeding even more, and have found it to be my true passion. Again, I love it in my own life, but I also love helping others to achieve their breastfeeding goals too! Lastly, I’m at home (most of the week). That means I’m trying thrifty things, I’m cooking all of the time, and I’m constantly trying to come up with ways to keep my baby girl safe and happy. Throw in some random abbreviation for being a crazy pet lady and my professional title could have replaced this entire blog post. I can’t decide if that’s cool or depressing…
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 18 Nov 2015 08:58:35 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://beansandboobiemilk.com/Introduction</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://beansandboobiemilk.com/Introduction</guid>
        
        
        <category>Self</category>
        
        <category>Reflection</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Wedding Etiquette</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;It’s time for a post that has nothing to do with beans, boobie milk, or babies in general! I mentally wrote this 3 years ago as a Facebook rant, but I hate Facebook rants, and it was too close to our actual wedding and I didn’t want to hurt anyone’s feelings. But enough time has passed, I think it’s time I speak my piece. 

&lt;p&gt;Rob and I got married when I was only 23. I was the first to get married of nearly everyone I knew, so it really felt like unchartered territory. Planning the wedding became my full-time job while I was between my dietetic internship and finding an actual big girl occupation. Each detail took days to decide and prep, and if I say so myself, we had one heck of a celebration.

&lt;p&gt;The one thing that truly bothered me about the entire experience was the lack of etiquette and manners that were followed by a majority of my friends. Like I said, it&#39;s been 3.5 years since then, and I&#39;m sure everyone has learned how to be a good wedding guest by now, so I don&#39;t mind saying, most of them were a huge hassle. So, just in case you still aren&#39;t sure of what is ok or not, here is a list of things that you should do in order to be a good little wedding guest.

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;1. RSVP. Actually do it. I know you get that cute invite and you get all excited for the big day, but that second card and/or website that is listed is there for a reason. Brides and grooms need counts and names to plan seating charts, meals, and expenses. They shouldn&#39;t have to track you down to see if you&#39;re coming. Let them know as soon as you do. If you miss the RSVP deadline, it’s too late. Much goes on behind the scenes of a wedding and changing the number of guests usually isn’t allowed or possible.

&lt;p&gt;2. When you submit your RSVP list EVERY person coming. If that number is larger than what was listed on your invitation, then you&#39;re doing it wrong. If your invite does give you a guest, make sure to tell the bride or groom who you are bringing And one last thing, for the love of Pete, don&#39;t just show up with an extra person that no one had any idea was coming.

&lt;p&gt;3. Don’t ask to bring a date. Plus-ones are a luxury at a wedding. Each person typically costs the couple $100, and when you are feeding 100 people that adds up fast. The bride (or groom) doesn&#39;t want to deal with feelings of guilt for telling you no, nor does she/he want an extra stranger at the biggest day of his/her life. A girl that asked to bring a date to my wedding recently got engaged and made an entire Facebook post begging people to stop asking for plus ones. The irony was overwhelmingly funny to me. 

&lt;p&gt;4. Bring a gift that you planned ahead. It&#39;s ok if that gift is simply a handwritten letter in an envelope. Although most couples expect you to spend money on them, that isn&#39;t the point of the celebration and it&#39;s ok if you can&#39;t afford it. But that doesn&#39;t mean you bring nothing. Some kind words of adoration or appreciation are still a nice gesture. Please also don&#39;t just hand one of them cash at the reception. Cash is great, but it&#39;s hard to keep track of during the busiest night of your life. When Rob and I got to our hotel he pulled out a huge wad of $20 bills but almost no memory of who handed him how much, etc. Put it in a card or mail it late. Don&#39;t give the couple homework.

&lt;p&gt;5. Express your gratitude. One way our guests didn&#39;t let us down was telling us how great a time they had at our wedding. As a bride, you spend a ton of time thinking about what other people will think about all your hard work. It’s very rewarding to be told that your efforts were noticed and appreciated. Rob and I still have people tell us our wedding was one of the best they&#39;ve ever attended. I have no clue if they are lying, but it puts a smile on my face regardless. If a wedding was truly a bummer, at least mention something about the decor, invitation, or details you know they spent time working on.

&lt;p&gt;I don&#39;t have any type of credentials for proper etiquette. I&#39;m not sure if those exist or not? But I was raised by a woman that believed strongly in thank you cards, manners, and fulfilling obligations. Being a good guest will not only make the couple happy, but when it comes time for your big day, you won&#39;t have to live with feelings of regret for how crappy you were to some other bride 2 years ago.

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 15 Nov 2015 08:58:35 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://beansandboobiemilk.com/Wedding</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://beansandboobiemilk.com/Wedding</guid>
        
        
        <category>Weddings</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
